Learning-SICP学习小组
倾情制作
教授：上节课中我们学习了如何构造语言
PROFESSOR: The last time we began having a look at how languages are constructed.
重点就是 像Lisp这样的求值器
Remember the main point that an evaluator for, LISP, say,
有两个主要部分
has two main elements.
一个是EVAL
There is EVAL,
EVAL接受一个表达式EXP和环境ENV
and EVAL's job is to take in an expression and an environment
然后返回一个过程和相关的实际参数
and turn that into a procedure and some arguments
并把它们传递给APPLY
and pass that off to APPLY.
APPLY接收这些过程和实际参数
And APPLY takes the procedure in the arguments,
通常来说 APPLY会返回另一个表达式
turns that back into, in a general case, another expression
返回另在另一个环境中求值的表达式
to be evaluated in another environment
表达式就像这样在EVAL-APPLY之间传递
and passes that off to EVAL, which passes it to APPLY,
这就是整个元循环
and there's this whole big circle
表达式在这里面循环往复
where things go around and around and around
直到最后求值为基本数据或基本过程
until you get either to some very primitive data or to a primitive procedure.
这个循环要做的就是
See, what this cycle has to do with
把语言中的组合手段
is unwinding the means of combination
和抽象手段展开
and the means of abstraction in the language.
比如说在Lisp中 你有一个过程
So for instance, you have a procedure in LISP--
定义过程是为了
a procedure is a general way of saying,
让表达式的计算过程
I want to be able to evaluate this expression
适用于任意的参数
for any value of the arguments,
这就是这里面发生的事情
and that's sort of what's going on here.
这就是APPLY做的事
That's what APPLY does.
当一个带参数的一般性表达式进入以后
It says the general thing coming in with the arguments
它将其归约为过程体的表达式
reduces to the expression that's the body,
如果归约得到的是复合表达式
and then if that's a compound expression
或者是另外的过程应用
or another procedure application,
那么这个循环就会不断地进行
the thing will go around and around the circle.
这基本上就是 -- 大部分解释器的基本结构了
Anyway, that's sort of the basic structure of gee, pretty much any interpreter.
另外一点就是
The other thing that you saw
一旦你有了一个解释器
once you have the interpreter in your hands,
你就有了操作这门语言的所有能力
you have all this power to start playing with the language.
因此你可以让它成为动态作用域
So you can make it dynamically scoped,
你也可以引入正则序求值
or you can put in normal order evaluation,
你也可以为语言添加新的形式
or you can add new forms to the language,
想怎么样都行
whatever you like.
或者更一般地说
Or more generally,
这种元语言抽象的概念
there's this notion of metalinguistic abstraction,
它告诉我们 作为一名软件工程师
which says that part of your perspective
从广义的“工程师”的角度来看
as an engineer, as a software engineer, but as an engineer in general
有时你可以通过发明新的语言
is that you can gain control of complexity
来获得控制复杂度的能力
by inventing new languages sometimes.
一种思考计算机程序设计的方法就是
See, one way to think about computer programming
它只是偶然地让计算机执行某事儿
is that it only incidentally has to do with getting a computer to do something.
计算机程序的主要工作却是
Primarily what a computer program has to do with,
用来表达和交流思想
it's a way of expressing ideas with communicating ideas.
有时
And sometimes
当我们想要表达新的思想时
when you want to communicate new kinds of ideas,
我们就想要发明新的模式来表达它们
you'd like to invent new modes of expressing that.
那么 今天我们就将按照这个框架来创建新语言
Well, today we're going to apply this framework to build a new language.
一旦我们了解了解释器的基本结构
See, once we have the basic idea of the interpreter,
我们就可以按意愿来构造任意的语言
you can pretty much go build any language that you like.
比如说 我们可以构造Pascal（的解释器）
So for example, we can go off and build Pascal.
以及
And...
我们需要操心语法的表示与解析
gee, we would worry about syntax and parsing
还有一大堆的编译器优化
and various kinds of compiler optimizations,
还有一些人会这样做
and there are people who make honest livings doing that,
但是就在我们所讨论的抽象层次来说
but at the level of abstraction that we're talking,
一个Pascal语言的解释器看起来
a Pascal interpreter would not look very different at all
跟Gerry教授上节课所讲的大同小异
from what you saw Gerry do last time.
但是今天 我们要构建一门与众不同的语言
Instead of that, we'll spend today building a really different language,
这门语言
a language that encourages you
不推荐你用过程式的思维来思考程序设计
to think about programming not in terms of procedures,
而是用一种非常不同的方式
but in a really different way.
今天的课程呢
And the lecture today is
将会在两个层次中同时进行
going to be at two levels simultaneously.
一方面
On the one hand,
我会向大家介绍这门语言是如何使用的
I'm going to show you what this language looks like,
另一方面呢 我会带领大家实现这门语言
and on the other hand, I'll show you how it's implemented.
我们将会用Lisp来实现
And we'll build an implementation in LISP
并观察它的运行原理
and see how that works.
你应该在两个层次上学到知识
And you should be drawing lessons on two levels.
首先要认识到 语言之间可以有多么地“不同”
The first is to realize just how different a language can be.
如果你认为Fortran和Lisp算是天差地别的话
So if you think that the jump from Fortran to LISP is a big deal,
那就小巫见大巫了
you haven't seen anything yet.
其次
And secondly,
甚至于在这门与众不同的语言中
you'll see that even with such a very different language,
这门既不讨论函数
which will turn out to not have procedures at all
也没有过程的语言中
and not talk about functions at all,
其中也有基本的EVAL-APPLY循环
there will still be this basic cycle of eval and apply
也就是对组合手段和抽象手段的展开
that's unwinds the means of combination and the means an abstraction.
第三点 是一个不太重要但非常优雅的技术技巧
And then thirdly, as kind of a minor but elegant technical point,
就是如何使用流来规避回溯
you'll see a nice use of streams to avoid backtracking.
好吧 我说过这门语言与众不同
OK, well, I said that this language is very different.
为了解释这点
To explain that,
让我们回到这门课最初的理念上
let's go back to the very first idea that we talked about in this course,
就是要区别
and that was the idea of the distinction between
数学中“陈述性”的知识
the declarative knowledge of mathematics--
比如平方根的定义就是一条数学事实
the definition of a square root as a mathematical truth--
而计算机科学讨论的是“如何做”的只是
and the idea that computer science talks about the how to knowledge--
“什么是平方根”和“如何计算平方根”是不同的
contrast that definition of square root with a program to compute a square root.
我们是从这里开始的
That's where we started off.
如果我们能够通过某种方式
Well, wouldn't it be great
弥合这种差距 岂不是更好么？
if you could somehow bridge this gap
我们创建一门这样的语言
and make a programming language which sort of did things,
以声明式的方式、用数学事实来完成计算
but you talked about it in terms of truth, in declarative terms?
你用这种该语言来指定事实
So that would be a programming language in which you specify facts.
你告诉它
You tell it what is.
什么是事实
You say what is true.
而当你需要一个答案时
And then when you want an answer,
语言已经自动地内建了
somehow the language has built into it automatically
有关于“如何做”的一般性知识
general kinds of how to knowledge
这样它就可以根据你给出的事实
so it can just take your facts
自行地演进这些方法
and it can evolve these methods on its own
通过你给定的事实和某种一般性的逻辑规则
using the facts you gave it and maybe some general rules of logic.
就比如说
So for instance,
我会告诉程序下述事实
I might go up to this program and start telling it some things.
我告诉它 (SON-OF ADAM ABEL)
So I might tell it that the son of Adam is Abel.
同时告诉它 (SON-OF ADAM CAIN)
And I might tell it that the son of Adam is Cain.
以及 (SON-OF CAIN ENOCH)
And I might tell it that the son of Cain is Enoch.
还有 (SON-OF ENOCH IRAD)
And I might tell it that the son of Enoch is Irad,
#TBD
and all through the rest of our chapter whatever of Genesis,
最后终止于ADAH
which ends up ending in Adah, by the way,
这些是从ADAH到CAIN的家谱
and this shows the genealogy of Adah from Cain.
总之 一旦你指明了这些事实
Anyway, once you tell it these facts,
你就可以提出问题
you might ask it things.
你可以对语言系统发问
You might go up to your language and say,
谁是ADAM的孩子？
who's the son of Adam?
可以很容易地想到一个通用搜索程序
And you can very easily imagine having a little general purpose search program
它会遍历所有的事实
which would be able to go through
然后回答：“哦 有两个答案”
and in response to that say, oh yeah, there are two answers:
ABEL是ADAM的孩子
the son of Adam is Abel
CAIN也是ADAM的孩子
and the son of Adam is Cain.
你也可以这样问
Or you might say,
基于同样的事实
based on the very same facts,
CAIN是谁的孩子？
who is Cain the son of?
你们就会想到生成另外一个略微不同的搜索程序
And then you can imagine generating another slightly different search program
它也会遍历所有的事实
which would be able to go through
检查谁的孩子是CAIN
and checked for who is Cain, and son of,
发现结果是ADAM
and come up with Adam.
你也可以问
Or you might say,
CAIN和ENOCH之间是什么关系？
what's the relationship between Cain and Enoch?
又会生成另一个略微不同的搜索程序
And again, a minor variant on that search program.
得到的结果是亲子关系（SON-OF）
You could figure out that it said son of.
在这个非常简单的例子中
But even here in this very simple example,
我们发现 即使是单条事实
what you see is that a single fact,
比如说 (SON-OF ADAM CAIN)
see, a single fact like the son of Adam is Cain
可以被用来回答不同种类的问题
can be used to answer different kinds of questions.
你可以问CAIN是谁的孩子？
You can say, who's Cain the son of,
你也可以问ADAM的孩子是谁？
or you can say who's the son of Adam,
你也可以问ADAM和CAIN之间的关系是什么？
or you can say what's the relation between Adam and Cain?
你也可以问ADAM的孩子是谁？
or you can say who's the son of Adam,
你也可以问ADAM和CAIN之间的关系是什么？
or you can say what's the relation between Adam and Cain?
这些由不同的传统程序
Those are different questions
所解答的不同的问题
being run by different traditional procedures
都基于同样的事实
all based on the same fact.
这正是这种程序设计风格的威力所在
And that's going to be the essence of the power of this programming style,
也就是一条陈述性知识
that one piece of declarative knowledge
可以作为大量关于“如何做”的各种知识的基础
can be used as the basis for a lot of different kinds of how-to knowledge,
这跟我们正在编写的过程是不同的
as opposed to the kinds of procedures we're writing
我们编写的过程描述了输入
where you sort of tell it what input you're giving in
以及想要的输出
and what answer you want.
比如说 我们的平方根程序可以完美地回答
So for instance, our square root program can perfectly well answer the question,
144的平方根是多少？
what's the square root of 144?
但从原理上来说
But in principle,
平方根的数学定义告诉了你另外的东西
the mathematical definition of square root tells you other things.
就比如说 17是谁的平方根
Like it could say, what is 17 the square root of?
这就需要另外一个程序来解答
And that would be have to be answered by a different program.
因此 数学定义
So the mathematical definition,
或者更一般地说
or in general, the
你给定的事实 对于问题是没有偏向性的
the facts that you give it are somehow unbiased as to what the question is.
而我们倾向于编写专门的程序
Whereas the programs we tend to write specifically
因为它们是关于“如何做”的知识
because they are how-to knowledge
倾向于寻找特定的答案
tend to be looking for a specific answer.
所以这是我们正在讨论的一个特点
So that's going to be one characteristic of what we're talking about.
然而我们可以更进一步
We can go on.
想象一下 我们可以向语言给定一些事实
We can imagine that we've given our language some sort of facts.
现在 我们给它一些推理规则
Now let's give it some rules of inference.
比如说
We can say, for instance,
这里 我们先用某种语法表示
if the-- make up some syntax here--
如果(SON-OF ?X ?Y)成立
if the son of x is y--
在这里 我用问号来标识变量
I'll put question marks to indicate variables here--
如果(SON-OF ?X ?Y)和(SON-OF ?Y ?Z)都成立
if the son of x is y and the son of y is z,
那么就有(GRANSON ?X ?Z)
then the grandson of x is z.
想象一下 如果把这条规则告诉机器
So I can imagine telling my machine that rule
那么我们就可以这么来询问
and then being able to say, for instance,
谁是ADAM的孙子？
who's the grandson of Adam?
或者说 IRAD是谁的孙子？
Or who is Irad the grandson of?
或者从这些信息中尽可能地推断出所有的祖孙关系
Or deduce all grandson relationships you possibly can from this information.
我们可以想象 语言知道如何自动求解
We can imagine somehow the language knowing how to do that automatically.
好吧 我再举一个更具体一点的例子
Ok, Let me give you maybe a little bit more concrete example.
这是个用来合并两个有序表的过程
Here's a procedure that merges two sorted lists.
X和Y是两个由数字构成的表
So x and y are two, say, lists of numbers,
我们可以认为它们是严格升序的表
lists of distinct numbers, if you like, that are in increasing order.
MERGE会把这两个表
And what merge does is take two such lists
合并成一个有序的表
and combine them into a list where everything's in increasing order,
这个程序非常简单
and this is a pretty easy programs
你们可以轻松地写出来
that you ought to be able to write.
也就是 如果X为空 那么结果就是Y
It says, if x is empty, the answer is y.
如果Y为空 那结果就是X
If y is empty, the answer is x.
否则的话 就要比较为首的两个元素
Otherwise, you compare the first two elements.
取出X中的第一个元素
So you pick out the first thing in x
以及Y中的第一个元素
and the first thing in y,
把它们当中谁是最小的那一个
and then depending on which of those first elements is less,
CONS在递归地调用MERGE的结果上
you stick the lower one on to the result a recursively merging,
要么就是(MERGE (CDR X) Y)
either chopping the first one off x
要么就是(MERGE X (CDR Y))
or chopping the first one off y.
这是标准的程序
That's a standard kind of program.
我们来考察下其中的逻辑
Let's look at the logic.
先不考虑程序
Let's forget about the program
来看看这个过程所基于的逻辑
and look at the logic on which that procedure is based.
这其中的逻辑是
See, there's some logic which says,
如果第一个元素较小
gee, if the first one is less,
那么最后的结果就是把它
then we get the answer by sticking something onto the
跟递归MERGE的结果CONS起来
the result of recursively merging the rest.
让我们试着把
So let's try and be explicit about
使这个程序运作的逻辑说清楚一点
what that logic is that's making the program work.
#TBD
So here's one piece.
这段程序
Here's the piece of the program which
递归地剥离X
recursively chops down x
如果X中的首元素较小的话
if the first thing in x is smaller.
如果要显式地指出其中的逻辑的话
And if you want to be very explicit about what the logic is there,
它其实就是演绎推理
what's really going on is a deduction,
其中 如果知道表CDR-X和表Y
which says, if you know that some list, that we'll call cdr of x, and y
能够通过MERGE-TO-FORM形成Z
merged to form z,
并且还知道A比Y中的第一个元素小
And you know that a is less than the first thing in y.
那么你就知道 如果你把A和CDR-X给CONS起来
then you know that if you put a onto the cdr of x.
得到的结果和Y一起
and that result and y
可以通过MERGE-TO-FORM形成Z
merge-to-form a onto z.
这就是它所基于的逻辑
And what that is, that's the underlying piece of logic--
我没有把它写成程序
I haven't written it as a program,
我把它写成了某种演绎
I wrote it a sort of deduction
正是属于这个特定子句的
that sits underneath this particular clause
它告诉我们可以在这里使用递归
that says we can use the recursion there.
同样地 这里还有些句子来补全其中的逻辑
And then similar, here's the other clause just to complete it.
其它的句子都是基于这些逻辑
The other clause is based on this piece of logic,
由于它们大部分是相同的 我就不细讲了
which is almost the same and I won't go through it,
然后就是终止条件
and then there's the end cases
是用来检查NULL的
where we tested for null,
其基本想法是 对于任意的X
and that's based on the idea that for any x,
X和空表可以通过MERGE-TO-FORM形成X
x and the empty list merge to form an x,
而空表可以和任意的Y通过MERGE-TO-FORM形成Y
or for any y, the empty list and y merge to form y.
这就是一段过程的代码
OK, so there's a piece of procedure
以及它所基于的逻辑
and the logic on which it's based.
请注意其中的巨大差异
And notice a big difference.
过程看起来是像这样的：
The procedure looked like this:
首先这有一个盒子
it said there was a box--
我们到目前为止所做的事都有这样的特征
and all the things we've been doing have the characteristic
我们有一个盒子 有东西进去 也有东西出来
we have boxes and things going in and things going out--
这儿有个MERGE盒子
there was this box called merge,
输入是X和Y
and in came an x and y,
输出ANS
and out came an answer.
这是我们所编写的程序的特征
That's the character of the procedure that we wrote.
但是规则并不像这样
These rules don't look like that.
规则讨论的是关系
These rules talk about a relation.
也就是在幻灯片中我称作MERGE-TO-FORM的关系
There's some sort of relation that in those slides I called mrege-to-form.
每当我说X和Y通过MERGE-TO-FORM形成Z
So I said x and y merge to form z,
这个是一个函数
and somehow this is not -- this is a function.
对吧？
Right?
ANS是X和Y的函数
The answer is a function of x and y,
而我这里得到的是三个东西之间的关系
and here what I have is a relation between three things.
我不会指明
And I'm not going to specify
哪个是输入 哪个是输出
which is the input and which is the output.
我之所以这么说 是因为原理上
And the reason I want to say that is because in principle,
我们可以用同样的逻辑规则
we could use exactly those same logic rules
来回答相当多的问题
answer a lot of different questions.
比如 我们可以问
So we can say, for instance-- giving
想象一下 如果把这些逻辑规则输入机器
imagine giving our machine those rules of logic.
不是输入程序 而是其中依赖的逻辑
Not the program, the underlying rules of logic.
那么 它也就应该回答--
Then it ought to be able to say--
我们可以问它
we could ask it--
(1 3 7)和(2 4 8)可以通过MERGE-TO-FORM形成什么？
1, 3, 7 and 2, 4, 8 merge to form what?
机器能够回答这样的问题
And that's a question it ought to be able to answer.
这同样也是我们的Lisp程序所回答的问题
That's exactly the same question that our Lisp procedure answered.
但这同样的规则
But the exact same rules
也能够回答像这样的问题：
should also be able to answer a question like this:
(1 3 7)和什么能够通过MERGE-TO-FORM形成(1 2 3 4 7 8)
1, 3, 7 and what merged to form 1, 2, 3, 4, 7, 8?
同样的逻辑规则也能够回答这个
The same rules of logic can answer this,
但我们编写的过程却无法回答这个问题
although the procedure we wrote can't answer that question.
又或者 我们可以问
Or we might be able to say what
什么和什么能通过MERGE-TO-FORM
what and what else merge to form--
哪两个东西可以通过MERGE-TO-FORM形成(1 2 3 4 7 8)？
what and what else merge to form 1, 2, 3, 4, 7, 8?
机器能够进行遍历
And the thing should be able to go through,
如果它能应用这些逻辑规则的话
if it really can apply that logic,
就能够推断出这个问题所有的2^6种答案
and deduce all, whatever is, 2 to the sixth answers to that question.
因为可以分别是 (1)和其余的
Cause it could be 1 and the rester, or it could be 1, 2 and the rest.
也可以是 (1 2)和其余的
or it could be 1, 2 and the rester.
也可以是(1 3 7)和其余的
Or it could be 1 and 3 and 7 and the rest.
有一大堆的答案
There's a whole bunch of answers.
但原理上来说 逻辑能推断出所有的答案
And in principle, the logic should be enough to deduce that.
因此这里面就有两个巨大的不同
So there are going to be two big differences
在我们所编写的程序中
in the kind of program we're going to look at
不只是Lisp程序
and not only Lisp,
基本上是你们目前编写过的所有程序
but essentially all the programming you've probably done so far
用你能叫出名字的程序语言所编写的程序
in pretty much any language you can think of.
首先 我们并不准备计算一个函数
The first is, we're not going to be computing functions.
我们将要讨论的东西
We're not going to be talking about
并不具有输入和输出
about things that take input and output.
我们讨论的是关系
We're going to be talking about relations.
也就是说 原理上 关系是没有方向性的
And that means in principle, these relations don't have directionality.
所以你指明用来回答这个问题的知识
So the knowledge that you specify to answer this question,
也同样应该能够反过来
should be same, that same knowledge
让你回答其它的这些问题
also allow you to answer these other questions and conversely.
其次则是
And the second issue is that
因为我们讨论的是关系
since we're talking about relations,
关系的答案并不唯一
these relations don't necessarily have one answer.
所以在第三个问题中
So that third question down there
并没有特定的答案
doesn't have a particular answer,
它有很多的答案
it has a whole bunch of answers.
这就是我们的目标
Well, that's where we're going.
顺便说一下
This style of programming,
这种程序设计风格被称作逻辑式程序设计
by the way, is called logic programming,
原因是显而易见的
for kind of obvious reasons.
用逻辑式进行程序设计的那群人之间
And people who do logic programming say that --
流传着几句箴言
they have this little phrase--
他们把逻辑式程序设计的要点归纳为
they say the point of logic programming
用逻辑来表达什么算是“真的”
is that you use logic to express what is true,
用逻辑来检测是否是“真的”
you use logic to check whether something is true,
用逻辑来找出这些“真的”
and you use logic to find out what is true.
最为大家所熟知的逻辑式程序设计语言
The best known logic programming language,
你们可能也听过 -- 叫做Prolog
as you probably know, is called Prolog.
今天早上我们将要实现的这门语言
The language that we're going to implement this morning
是一种查询语言
is something we call the query language,
它基本上就是Prolog的本质了
and it essentially has the essence of prolog.
它可以完成相同的工作
It can do about the same stuff,
虽然它比Prolog慢得多
although it's a lot slower
这是因为我们是通过Lisp来解释的
because we're going to implement it in LISP
而非构造一个专门的编译器
rather than building a particular compiler.
对它的解释 将运行在Lisp解释器之上
We're going to interpret it on top of the LISP interpreter.
除此之外 它可以完成与Prolog相同的事儿
But other than that, it can do about the same stuff as prolog.
不但同样的能力 也有同样的局限
It has about the same power and about the same limitations.
好吧 先解答一下疑惑
All right, let's break for question.
学生：您能再重复一下
STUDENT: Yes, could you please repeat what the three
用逻辑去寻找的三件事么？
things you use logic programming to find?
就是那些 找出什么为真 知道什么是真 等等
In other words, to find what is true, learn what is true-- what is the?
教授：好的
PROFESSOR: Right.
这算是程序员的某种“教义问答”
Sort of a logic programmer's little catechism.
我们用逻辑来表达怎么算是“真的”
You use logic to express what is true,
就像这些规则一样
like these rules.
我们用逻辑来检测某事是否是“真的”
You use logic to check whether something is true,
但在这里我没有回答这个问题
and that's the kind of question I didn't answer here.
我可以问
I might say--
在这里我可以这样来问
another question I could put down here is to say,
(1 3 7)和(2 4 8)是否能够
is it true that 1, 3, 7 and 2, 4, 8
通过MERGE-TO-FORM形成(1 2 6 19)
merge to form 1, 2, 6, 10
同样的逻辑规则会告诉我们不行
And that same logic should be enough to say no.
这里 我使用逻辑来检测是否为真
So I use logic to check what is true,
然后 我们也可以使用逻辑来找出为真的东西
and then you also use logic to find out what's true.
休息一下吧
Let's break.
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师：哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
逻辑式程序设计
教授：让我们继续来看一看
PROFESSOR: OK, let's go ahead and
这个查询语言及其操作
take a look at this query language and operation.
首先需要注意到
The first thing you might notice,
当我建立好那个小型的圣经数据库后
when I put up that little biblical database,
我们就能够针对一系列的事实
is that it's nice to be able to ask this language questions
以关系的方式来向这个语言提问
in relation to some collection of facts.
因此 我们先来陈述一些事实
So let's start off and make a little collection of facts.
这是波士顿一家高科技公司的
This is a tiny fragment of personnel records
一小部分人事档案
for a Boston high tech company,
这部分档案是Ben Bitdiddle的
and here's a piece of the personnel records of Ben Bitdiddle.
Bitdiddle是这家公司的计算机向导
And Ben Bitdiddle is the computer wizard in this company,
他是这家公司的低薪向导
he's the underpaid computer wizard in this company.
他的上司是Oliver Warbucks
His supervisor is all Oliver Warbucks,
这里是他的住址
and here's his address.
我们按照这样的格式给出信息：职务、薪水、上司、住址
So the format is we're giving this information: job, salary, supervisor, address.
还有一些其它的约定
And there are some other conventions.
这里的COMPUTER表示BEN在计算机分部工作
Computer here means that Ben works in the computer division, and
而他在这个分部的工作是向导
his position in the computer division is wizard.
这里是其他人的
Here's somebody else.
ALyssa P.Hacker是一名计算机程序员
Alyssa, Alyssa P. Hacker is a computer programmer,
她的上司是Ben
and she works for Ben,
而她住在Cambridge
and she lives in Cambridge.
Ben手下的另外一个程序员
And there's another programmer who works for Ben
叫做Lem E. Tweakit
who's Lem E. Tweakit.
实习程序员 Louis Reasoner
And there's a programmer trainee, who is Louis Reasoner,
在Alyssa手下工作
and he works for Alyssa.
公司里的“老大哥”不为任何人工作
And the big wheel of the company doesn't work for anybody.
这就是Oliver Warbucks的档案了
Right, That's Oliver Warbucks.
我们将要做的就是
Anyway, what we're going to do is
对这个小型的世界提问
is ask questions about that little world.
这将是我们进行逻辑运算的样本世界
And that'll be a sample world that we're going to do logic in.
我再最后一次强调一下
Let me just write up here, for probably the last time,
你们应该从这门课中学到的最重要的知识
what I said is the very most important thing you should get out of this course,
也就是 当别人向你介绍语言时
and that is, when somebody tells you about a language,
你要问：“它的基本元素是什么？”
you say, fine-- what are the primitives,
组合的手段有哪些？
what are the means of combination,
如何把基本元素组织在一起
how do you put the primitives together,
然后把它们抽象出来？and then how do you abstract them,
如何抽象这些复合元素
how do you abstract the compound pieces
以便于你能够复用它们构造更复杂的东西？
so you can use them as pieces to make something more complicated?
我已经强调过很多次了
And we've said this a whole bunch of times already,
但还是值得重申一遍
but it's worth saying again.
记住了么？我们开始了
OKay? Let's start.
首先是基本元素
The primitives.
这其中 只有唯一的基本元素
Well, there's really only one primitive,
这门语言中的基本元素就是“查询”
and the primitive in this language is called a query.
一条基本查询
A primitive query.
我们先来看几条基本查询
Let's look at some primitive queries.
首先 这条查询问的是
Alright. Job x.
“谁是计算机程序员？”
Who is a computer programmer?
或者可以解释为：找出数据库中
Or find every fact in the database
所有JOB栏为COMPUTER PROGRAMMER的事实
that matches job of the x is computer programmer.
这里有一些小语法
And you see a little syntax here.
不带问号的都是字面量
Things without question marks are meant to be literal,
?X表示X是变量
question mark x means that's a variable,
而这条查询会匹配 比如说 --
and this thing will match, for example,
Alyssa P. Hacker 是程序员
the fact that Alyssa P. Hacker is a computer programmer,
其中X为Alyssa P. Hacker这条事实
or x is Alyssa P. Hacker.
Or more generally, I could have something with two variables in it.
I could say, the job of x is computer something, and that'll match computer wizard.
So there's something here: type will match wizard, or type will match programmer, or x might match various certain things.
So there are, in our little example, only three facts in that database that match that query.
Let's see, just to show you some syntax, the same query, this query doesn't match the job of x, doesn't match Lewis Reasoner, the reason for that is when I write something here, what I mean is that this is going to be a list of two symbols, of which the first is the word computer, and the second can be anything.
And Lewis's job description here has three symbols, so it doesn't match.
And just to show you a little bit of syntax, the more general thing I might want to type is a thing with a dot here, and this is just standard this notation for saying, this is a list, of which the first element is the word computers, and THE REST, is something that I'll call type.
So this one would match.
Lewis's job is computer programmer trainee, and type here would be the cdr of this list. It would be the list programmer trainee.
And that kind of dot processing is done automatically by the LISP reader.
Well, let's actually try this.
The idea is I'm going to type in queries in this language, and answers will come out.
Let's look at this.
I can go up and say, who works in the computer division?
Job of x is computer dot y.
Doesn't matter what I call the dummy variables.
It says the answers to that, and it's found four answers.
Or I can go off and say, tell me about everybody's supervisor.
So I'll put in the query, the primitive query, the supervisor of x is y.
There are all the supervisor relationships I know.
Or I could go type in, who lives in Cambridge?
So I can say, the address of x is Cambridge dot anything.
And only one person lives in Cambridge.
OK, so those are primitive queries.
And you see what happens to basic interaction with the system is you type in a query, and it types out all possible answers.
Or another way to say that: it finds out all the possible values of those variables x and y or t or whatever I've called them, and it types out all ways of taking that query and instantiating it-- remember that from the rule system lecture-- instantiates the query with all possible values for those variables and then types out all of them.
And there are a lot of ways you can arrange a logic language.
Prolog, for instance, does something slightly different.
Rather than typing back your query, prolog would type out, x equals this and y equals that, or x sequels this and y equals that.
And that's a very surface level thing, you can decide what you like.
OK.
Alright. So the primitives in this language?
Only one, right?
Primitive query.
Means of combination.
Let's look at some compound queries in this language.
Here's one.
This one says, tell me all the people who work in the computer division.
Tell me all the people who work in the computer division together with their supervisors.
The way I write that is the query is and.
And the job of the x is computer something or other.
And job of x is computer dot y.
And the supervisor of x is z.
Tell me all the people in the computer division-- that's this-- together with their supervisors.
And notice in this query I have three variables-- x, y, and z.
And this x is supposed to be the same as that x.
So x works in the computer division, and the supervisor of x is z.
Let's try another one.
So one means of combination is and.
Who are all the people who make more than $30,000?
And the salary of some person p is some amount a.
And when I go and look at a, a is greater than $30,000.
And LISP value here is a little piece of interface that interfaces the query language to the underlying LISP.
And what the LISP value allows you to do is call any LISP predicate inside a query.
So here I'm using the LISP predicate greater than, so I say LISP value.
This I say and.
So all the people whose salary is greater than $30,000.
Or here's a more complicated one.
Tell me all the people who work in the computer division who do not have a supervisor who works in the computer division.
and x works in the computer division.
The job of x is computer dot y.
And it's not the case that both x has a supervisor z and the job of z is computer something or other.
All right, so again, this x has got to be that x, and this z is going to be that z.
And then you see another means a combination, not.
All right, well, let's look at that.
It works the same way.
I can go up to the machine and say and the job of the x is computer dot y.
And the supervisor of x is z.
And I typed that in like a query.
And what it types back, what you see are the queries I typed in instantiated by all possible answers.
And then you see there are a lot of answers.
All right.
So the means of combination in this language-- and this is why it's called a logic language-- are logical operations.
Means of combinations are things like AND and NOT and there's one I didn't show you, which is OR.
And then I showed you LISP value, which is not logic, of course, but is a little special hack to interface that to LISP so you can get more power.
Those are the means of combination.
OK, the means of abstraction.
What we'd like to do--  let's go back for second and look at that last slide.
We might like to take very complicated thing, the idea that someone works in a division but does not have a supervisor in the division.
And as before, name that.
Well, if someone works in a division and does not have a supervisor who works in that division, that means that person is a big shot.
So let's make a rule that somebody x is a big shot in some department if x works in the department and it's not the case that x has a supervisor who works in the department.
So this is our means of abstraction.
This is a rule.
And a rule has three parts.
The thing that says it's a rule.
And then there's the conclusion of the rule.
And then there's the body of the rule.
And you can read this as a piece of logic which says, if you know that the body of the rule is true, then you can conclude that the conclusion is true.
Or in order to deduce that x is a big shot in some department, it's enough to verify that.
So that's what rules look like.
Let's go back and look at that merge example that I did before the break.
Let's look at how that would look in terms of rules.
I'm going to take the logic I put up and just change it into a bunch of rules in this format.
We have a rule.
Remember, there was this thing merge-to-form.
There is a rule that says, the empty list and y merge to form y.
This is the rule conclusion.
And notice this particular rule has no body.
And in this language, a rule with no body is something that is always true.
You can always assume that's true.
And there was another piece of logic that said anything in the empty list merged to form the anything.
That's this.
A rule y and the empty list merge to form y.
Those corresponded to the two end cases in our merge procedure, but now we're talking about logic, not about procedures.
Then we had another rule, which said if you know how shorter things merge, you can put them together.
So this says, if you have a list x and y and z, and if you want to deduce that a dot x-- this means constant a onto x, or a list whose first thing is a and whose rest is x-- so if you want to deduce that a dot x and b dot y merge to form b dot c--  that would say you merge these two lists a x and b y and you're going to get something that starts with b-- you can deduce that if you know that it's the case both that a dot x and y merge to form z and a is larger than b.
So when I merge them, b will come first in the list. That's a little translation of the logic rule that I wrote in pseudo-English before.
And then just for completeness, here's the other case.
a dot x and b dot y merge to form a dot z if x and b dot y merged to form z and b is larger than a.
So that's a little program that I've typed in in this language, and now let's look at it run.
So I typed in the merge rules before, and I could use this like a procedure.
I could say merge to form 1 and 3 and 2 and 7.
So here I'm using it like the LISP procedure.
Now it's going to think about that for a while and apply these rules.
So it found an answer.
Now it's going to see if there are any other answers but it doesn't know a priori there's only one answer.
So it's sitting here checking all possibilities, and it says, no more.
So it's sitting here checking all possibilities, and it says, no more. Done.
So there I've used those rules like a procedure.
Or remember the whole point is that I can ask different kinds of questions.
I could say merge to form, let's see, how about 2 and a.
Some list of two elements which I know starts with 2, and the other thing I don't know, and x and some other list merge to form a 1, 2, 3 and 4.
So now it's going to think about that.
It's got to find--  so it found one possibility.
It said a could be 3, and x could be the list 1, 4.
And now, again, it's got to check because it doesn't a priori know that there aren't any other possibilities going on.
Or like I said, I could say something like merge to form, like, what and what else merge to form 1, 2, 3, 4, 5?
Now it's going to think about that.
And there are a lot of answers that it might get.
And what you see is here you're really paying the price of slowness.
And kind of for three reasons.
One is that this language is doubly interpreted.
Whereas in a real implementation, you would go compile this down to primitive operations.
The other reason is that this particular algorithm for merges is doubly recursive.
So it's going to take a very long time.
And eventually, this is going to go through and find-- find what?
Two to the fifth possible answers.
And you see they come out in some fairly arbitrary order, depending on which order it's going to be trying these rules.
In fact, what we're going to do when they edit the videotape is speed all this up.
Don't you like taking out these weights?
And don't you wish you could do that in your demos?
Anyway, it's still grinding there.
Anyway, there are 32 possibilities-- we won't wait for it to print out all of them.
OK, so the needs of abstraction in this language are rules.
So we take some bunch of things that are put together with logic and we name them.
And you can think of that as naming a particular pattern of logic.
Or you can think of that as saying, if you want to deduce some conclusion, you can apply those rules of logic.
And those are three elements of this language.
Let's break now, and then we'll talk about how it's actually implemented.
STUDENT: Does using LISP value primitive or whatever interfere with your means to go both directions on a query?
PROFESSOR: OK, that's a-- the question is, does using LISP value interfere with the ability to go both directions on the query?
We haven't really talked about the implementation yet, but the answer is, yes, it can.
In general, as we'll see at the end-- although I really won't to go into details-- it's fairly complicated, especially when you use either not or LISP value-- or actually, if you use anything besides only and, it becomes very complicated to say when these things will work.
They won't work quite in all situations.
I'll talk about that at the end of the second half today.
But the answer to your question is, yes, by dragging in a lot more power from LISP value, you lose some of the principal power of logic programming.
That's a trade-off that you have to make.
OK, let's take a break.
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/DeathKing/Learning-SICP